Guide to the Irving Miller Collection of World War II Posters
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Irving Miller collection of World War II posters
1942-1943
MS 1845
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
The collection consists primarily of World War II posters designed by Irving Miller and created by various artists, including Henry Koerner and Robert Gwathmey, for the Office of War Information and other government agencies. A few posters by other artists are included at the end of the collection.
Miller, Irving, 1918-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jon Miller, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The Irving Miller Collection of World War II Posters is arranged alphabetically by the government agency for which the posters were produced. Within a department, the posters are arranged alphabetically by title. When known, the artist's name is provided, followed by the size of the poster.
Biographical / Historical
Irving Miller was born on December 7, 1918, in New York City. While a student at City College of New York, he designed book jackets for Random House, MacMillan, Alfred A. Knopf, Dodd Mead and Harper and freelanced for the newly formed CBS radio network. Upon graduation in 1939, he taught the first course in graphic design offered by City College. During World War II, he joined the Office of War Information (OWI) as the art director of war posters, working with leading artists such as Norman Rockwell, Ben Shahn, David Stone Martin, and others to produce a wide range of posters. He was later appointed art director of the OWI. Following the end of the war, he was appointed art director at CBS where he received numerous awards. Some of his work was published in major graphic design magazines and was featured in several highly successful one-man shows. He left CBS in 1958 to open his own graphic design studio on Lexington Avenue where, over the next twenty-five years, he worked for major clients such as IBM, International Paper, Westvaco, American Bank Note, and the Roman Catholic Church. Following his retirement in 1995, he continued in the graphic design field, as well as fine art painting.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of World War II posters designed by Irving Miller and created by various artists, including Henry Koerner and Robert Gwathmey, for the Office of War Information and other government agencies. A few posters by other artists are included at the end of the collection.
World War, 1939-1945 -- Posters; Posters; Miller, Irving, 1918-; United States. Office of War Information
- Department of Agriculture
  - Food Comes First. [Glenn Grohe, 26 x 20], 1943 (Box 1)
- Federal Security Agency
  - Enlist in a Proud Profession! Join the U.S. Cadet Nurse Corps. [Edmundson, 20 x 28], undated (Box 1)
- Office of Price Administration
  - Rationing means a fair share for all of us. [Al Dorn, 22 x 28], 1943 (Box 1)
- Office of War Information
  - America's Fishing Fleet and Men...Assets to Victory. [Henry Koerner, OWI poster no. 61, 28 x 21], 1943 (Box 1)
  - A careless word...another cross. [John Atherton, OWI poster no. 23, 22 x 28], 1943 (Box 1)
  - Do with less--so they'll have enough! Rationing gives you your fair share. [artist unidentified, OWI poster no. 37, 28 x 22], 1943 (Box 1)
  - Easy to Get...Syphilis and Gonorrhea [artist unidentified, 14 x 20], 1943 (Box 2)
  - Fish is a Fighting Food, We Need More. [Henry Koerner, OWI poster no. 60, 28 x 20], 1943 (Box 2)
  - Food is a Weapon, Don't waste it! [Henry Koerner, OWI poster no. 60, 28 x 20], 1943 (Box 2)
  - Help Bring Them Back to You! Make Yours a Victory Home! [artist unidentified, OWI poster no. 41, 22 x 28], 1943 (Box 2)
  - "I'll carry mine too!" [Sarra, OWI poster no. 28, 28 x 22], 1943 (Box 2)
  - I've Found the Job Where I Fit Best! Find your war job in Industry--Agriculture--Business. [artist unidentified, OWI poster no. 55, 16 x 22½], 1943 (Box 2)
  - Keep Him Flying! Buy War Bonds. [artist unidentified, 28 x 22], 1943 (Box 3)
  - The more Women at work the sooner we Win! [artist unidentified, OWI poster no. 52, 14 x 22] (Box 3)
  - Plant a Victory Garden. [Robert Gwathmey, OWI poster no. 34, 28 x 22], 1943 (Box 3)
  - Save waste fats for explosives. [Henry Koerner, OWI poster no. 63, 28 x 20], 1943 (Box 3)
  - Strong in the Strength of the Lord we who fight in the people's cause will never stop until that cause is won. [David Stone Martin, OWI poster no. 8, 21 x 28], 1942 (Box 3)
  - This man may die...if you talk too much. [Sarra, OWI poster no. 6, 22 x 28], 1943 (Box 4)
  - United We are Strong United We Will Win. [Henry Koerner, OWI poster no. 61, 28 x 21], 1943 (Box 4)
  - Use it up--Wear it out--Make it do! Our labor and our goods are fighting. [Robert Gwathmey, OWI poster no. 39, 28 x 22], 1943 (Box 4)
  - War Shipments Mean Less Fuel for All. [artist unidentified, OWI poster no. 29, 22 x 28], 1943 (Box 4)
  - We French workers warn you...defeat means slavery, starvation, death. [Ben Shahn, OWI poster no. 17, 28 x 40], 1942 (Box 4)
  - "We'll have lots to eat this winter, won't we Mother?" Grow your own, can your own. [Al Parker, OWI poster no. 57, 22 x 14], 1943 (Box 5)
  - Where our men are fighting our food is fighting. [Robert Gwathmey, OWI poster no. 35, 28 x 22], 1943 (Box 5)
  - Work on a Farm this Summer. [Douglas, OWI poster no. 59, 16 x 22½], 1943 (Box 5)
- War Production Board
  - If it'll save a second it's a great idea--let's have it! [Henry Koerner, 28 x 40], 1943 (Box 5)
  - Next of kin has been notified...your work will save lives. [Xavier Gonzalez, War Production Board poster no. 828, 28 x 40], 1942 (Box 5)
- Other
  - Dali, Salvador [untitled design donated to OWI, never used due to sensitive nature of material, copyright status unknown, 11 x 13½], undated (Box 6)
  - For Their Sake...Avoid Veneral Disease. [artist unidentified, 14 x 20], 1943 (Box 6)
  - I pay no more than top legal prices--I accept no rationed goods without giving up ration stamps. [decal; artist unidentified, 5 x 5], undated (Box 6)
  - Norman Rockwell's Four Freedoms [poster depicting drawings of the four freedoms with descriptive history, 8½ x 11] (Box 6)
  - Your War Bonds are a Stake in the Future [Alan Sallburg, 20 x 28], 1943 (Box 6)